-=THE LAST FANTASY=-   榮譽出品   本字幕僅供學習交流，嚴禁用於商業用途
-=TLF字幕組=-   翻譯：pizzamx   校對：pizzamx
片名：猿球崛起
很好…給你
Hey, okay ...  now...
再來一次
let's go again.
- 這是哪一隻，九號？   - 沒錯，九號，「慧眼」
Which one's this, number9?  - Yeah, number 9.  Bright eyes.
你看到了嗎？
Are you watching this?
太不可思議了
This, this is unbelieveable.
上帝啊
Oh, my God.
- 一共多少步？   - 20
How many moves was that?  - 20.
最優算法是15步   天，你到底給她餵了什麼？
The perfect score is 15.  God, what, what are you giving her?
喂，把錄像給我！
Hey, give me that video!
九號黑猩猩，只注射了一支
Chimp number 9, just one dose.
- 沒見我忙著嗎？   - 我們準備好了
Couldn't I see you later?  - We're good to go.
我一會兒給你打回去   嗯，謝謝，再見
I'm going to call you back. Yeah,  all right.  Thanks, Bye.
112型藥劑，成功了
112, it works.
- 就在一隻身上成功了？   - 一隻就足夠了
On just the one primate?  - One is all we need.
智力完全復原
Full cognitive recovery.
我們準備好了
We're ready.
你確定不會太冒進？
Look, are you sure you're  not rushing this?
我已經試驗了五年半
I've been working on this for  five and a half years.
你一看數據便知，我們準備好了，史蒂芬
The data is clear.  We're ready, Steven.
只要你同意人體實驗即可
All I need is your approval  for human trials.
這得要董事會同意才行
Oh, for this, you're going to need  the Board's approval.
我們在這上面押了很多錢，威爾
There's a lot of money riding  on this, Will.
- 你只有一次機會   - 一次足矣
You only get one shot.  - One shot is all I need.
[sighs]
好，整理報告給我看
All right. I'll need to see  all the research.
沒問題
You got it!
- 還有，威爾…   - 嗯？
Oh, and Will ...  - Yeah?
不要把個人感情帶進來
Keep your personal emotions  out of it.
老闆們只看結果，別談什麼理想
These people invest in results,  not dreams.
好！
Okay!
這是九號黑猩猩，她正在做漢諾塔遊戲
Meet chimp 9. Here she's tasking at  what is called the Lucas Tower.
鐵盤在柱子之間移動
The object of which is to move the tower  from peg to peg
且大盤子不能壓在小盤子上面
without placing a larger block  on top of a smaller block.
跟我們預想的一樣，她失敗了
As expected, she was unable  to complete the puzzle at all.
然後我們對她進行了基因治療   藥劑名叫ALZ-112
Then, we gave her what we call,  ALZ-112, a gene therapy
它能使腦細胞自我修復
that allows the brain to create its  own cells in order to repair itself.
這在生物學上稱為「神經形成」
In biology, this is  called neurogenesis.
基因系統公司認為
Here, at GEN-SYS,
它能治癒老年癡呆癥
we call it a cure to Alzheimer's.
- 唐尼，讓她準備好，行嗎？   - 她應該是怯場了
Donnie, you get her ready?  - She's got stage fright.
真的嗎？
Is that what it is?
喂，猩猩
Hey, ape.
她會扯斷我的胳膊的！
She's gonna break my arm!
慧眼！放手！
Bright Eyes!  Let go!
沒事吧？
Are you all right?
我們已經準備好進入下個階段
We're ready to move  on to the next phase.
人體實驗
Human trials.
給你，慧眼，你最喜歡的泡沫蘇打
Here you go, Bright Eyes.  It's your favorite fizzy soda.
準備好，唐尼
Come on, let's go, Donnie.
她應該出場了
We should have her downstairs already.
很好，乖！
Okay. Good girl!
來啊，小姑娘，沒事的
Come on out, girl, that's right.
給你的
That's for you.
抓住了！
Got her!
天吶！
Jesus!
唐尼！把籠子打開！快打開！
Donnie, open the cage!  Open up! Open up!
我用鎮定劑！
Going to sedate her!
- 天吶！   - 快關門！
No, no!  - Get the door!
快抓住它，快！
No, no! Hold it! Now!
快叫人！唐尼，唐尼！
Call help! Donnie, Donnie!
對於112型藥劑，我們沒有發現任何副作用
There have been absolutely no side  effects associated
with 112, with one exception.
只是觀察到
For some reason,
猩猩的虹膜出現了綠點
the chimps irises exhibit  flecks of green.
我們也是在九號猩猩身上首次發現的
Actually, we first noticed it in chimp 9,
所以我們叫她「慧眼」
hence her nickname, Bright Eyes.
待會兒你們就能看到她了
You'll see when we bring her in.
快跑！
Move!
理論上，這種療法可以治療多種腦部疾病
In theory, this therapy  can be used
to treat a wide range  of brain disorders.
可以說前途無限
It's virtually limitless.
錢途也是無限
As are the potential profits.
所以我們相信
which is why we are confident that
大家會同意人體實驗的
you will vote to approve human trials.
天吶，快跑！
No, no, no!
雅各布斯先生，我求你了
Mr. Jacobs, Mr. Jacobs I am begging you,
我求你了，別這樣
I am begging you, not to do this.
聽著，給這些猩猩都做一遍檢查
Look, it costs a small fortune to
是要花不少錢的
run lab workups on all of those chimps
況且結果我現在已經知道
only to tell me what I already know,
它們被感染了
that they are contaminated.
這都是生命啊
There are lives at stake here.
這些動物是有靈性的
These, these are animals  with personalities,
我們已經有了感情
with attachments.
- 感情？   - 是的
Attachments?  - Yeah.
我是做生意的，不是開寵物樂園的
I run a a business,  not a petting zoo.
用最省錢的辦法把它們處理了吧
Find the most cost effective way  to put those apes down.
我下不了手
I can't do that.
你就是負責處理猩猩的
You're the chimp handler.
處理好
Handle it.
史蒂芬！
Steven!
表演很不錯！
Well, that was fun!
他們拿走了112藥劑
They've taken the 112.
董事會拒絕了你的提議
Board has rejected your proposal.
他們決定投資其他項目
They've chosen to advance other programs.
你一定還有辦法的
Well, there must be something  that you can do.
沒錯，比如炒了你
Yes. There is, I could fire you.
相信我，都說好的
Believe me, we talked about it.
五年實實在在的數據
We have five years of conclusive data.
你就賣弄你的數據吧
Parade all the data you want,
沒人再會投資一分錢了
you will never convince anyone  to invest another dime.
這種藥劑可能可以救人命啊！
This drug has the potential  to save lives!
我怎麼覺得它只能讓公司倒閉
Bankrupt this company, more like.
在我看來，你還是不瞭解人腦運作的機制
I swear, you know everything  about the human brain
except the way it works.
回到黑板前去吧
Go back to the drawing board  on the 112.
再從分子重新開始研究
Start again in  molecular development.
別被別人搶先了
Find a way to get there  before someone else does.
還有，給我收拾好實驗室
And, clean up this mess.
富蘭克林！
Franklin!
它還小，可能九號進來時已經懷孕了
It's very small. She must have been
pregnant when we brought her in.
所以她…
So that's why ...
她並非突然狂躁，而是在保護孩子
She wasn't being aggressive.  She was just being protective.
她以為我們要傷害她的孩子
She thought we were going to  hurt her baby.
我本想帶走它
I would take it myself,
但我姐夫是這堛澈O安，我不能害他
but my brother-in-law works for security.  He'd rat me out in a seceond.
你想讓我帶回家？
What, you want me to take it home?
我可照顧不了猴子
I can't take care of a monkey.
- 他不是猴子，是猩猩！   - 富蘭克林…
He's not a monkey! He's an ape.  - Franklin ...
你就照顧他幾天
You know, it's just for a couple days until
我很快就會找到收留所，拜託了
I find a sanctuary.  That's all I need.
別啊，富蘭克林！
Franklin, no!
這不是我的職責
Look, this isn't my responsibility.
而且這是公家的東西
This, this is company property.
好吧…
Okay ...
實話跟你說，博士
I tell you what, Doc.
雅各布斯讓我處理掉剩下的12只
Jacobs made me put down the other 12.
我不幹了
I'm done.
悉聽尊便
Be my guest.
Hey!  - Oh, hi.
- 你很累的樣子   - 嗯，他怎樣？
You look beat.  - Yeah. How's he doing?
老樣子，時好時壞
Well, he has good days and bad days.
今天雖然不是很好
Today, not so good, although he
但也說了幾句莎士比亞的台詞
has been quoting Shakespeare.
噢，養寵物了？
Oh, you got a pet?
呃，只是臨時收留
Uh, it's just a temporary house guest.
也許能跟他做個伴
Well, maybe that'll be good for him.
晚安！
Good night!
（獻給敬愛的音樂老師：查爾斯·羅德曼先生）
[discordant piano playing]
嗨，老爸！
Hi, Dad!
爸？
Dad?
威爾！沒聽見你進來
Will! I didn't hear  you come in.
是今天吧？
Today's the day, right?
以為我忘了？
You thought I'd forget?
你今天有重要考試對吧？
You have a big test today, right?
化學？
Chemistry?
呃，爸…
Hey, Dad ...
- 要不要看樣東西？   - 什麼？
You want to see something?  - What?
怎麼了，他受傷了？
What is that? Is he injured?
不，應該是胎記
No, I think that's a birthmark.
「可是對於凱撒，他只有跪伏驚嘆的份」   （莎士比亞作品《埃及艷後》，第三幕台詞）
"As for Caesar, kneel down,  kneel down and wonder!"
嗯，別玩出感情來了
Yeah, don't get too attached.
真可愛，是吧？
He's a cute little guy, isn't he?
我的車鑰匙呢？
Where's my car keys?
你把我車鑰匙放哪堨h了？
My car keys, where'd you put 'em?
爸，你…已經不再開車了
Dad, ... you a, you don't drive anymore.
我知道
I know that.
給你…
Here ...
給他餵奶，你會吧？
Why don't you feed him.  Can you do that?
什麼話，當然…
Of course, I can..
威爾！你來看！
Will! ... Look at this!
他幾歲了，一天還是兩天？
How old is he?  Like, a day old? Two days old?
嗯…
Yeah ...
他很聰明，是吧？
He's a smart one, isn't he?
你準備叫他什麼？
What are you going to name him?
我還沒想過…
I do not know ...
（三年後）
Three years later
很快，凱撒就顯示出超乎一般的智商
Right away, Caesar displayed signs  of intelligence heightened intelligence,
於是我留下了他，同時把工作帶回了家
so I kept him.   And, brought  my work home.
他十八個月時便認識了24個單詞
By 18 months,  Caesar was signing up to 24 words.
兩歲時，他已經在玩為八歲以上小孩設計的玩具
By age two,  Caesar completing puzzles and models
designed for children  eight years and up.
三歲時
At age three,
凱撒的認知能力
Caesar continues to show cognative skills
已經完全超越同齡的人類
that far exceed  that of his human counterpart.
家…家
Home ... home.
他15步就能完成漢諾塔，最優算法
He completed the Lucas Tower in  15 moves, a perfect score.
對此我認為，他虹膜堛犖韘漻\r}
I maintain my hypothesis that:  A. The green in his eyes indicate
表明他從母親身上遺傳了ALZ-112
that the ALZ-112 was passed  genetically from mother to son
並且在沒有受損腦細胞需要修補的情況下
and, B. That in the absence of damaged  cells that need to be replacing
這種藥劑能夠極大加速正常腦細胞的發育
the drug in his system has radically  boosted healthy brain functioning.
另外…
And, ...
他棋下得很好
he plays chess pretty well.
[shouting]
爸！
Dad!
- 不好意思   - 我受夠了
I'm sorry.  - I can't do this, anymore.
他應該去養老院
He belongs in a home.
他活不了多久了
This is no way for him to live.
活不了多久了？
No way to live?
我摔壞了檯燈…
I broke my lamp ...
我會讓你好起來的，爸爸
It'll make you better, Dad.
[Shhh...]
爸！
Dad!
[exuberant piano playing]
托德，來吃早飯
Todd, come inside for breakfast.
我得把實驗數據記錄下來
I'll need to keep track of  what I take from the lab,
不過我覺得你已經不用一個月治療一次了
although I don't see you needing  more than one treatment a month.
感覺太神奇了！
Something amazing has happened!
我要驗一下血，做個掃瞄
I'll need a blood test,  a scan and the dosage ...
還有注意劑量
carefully monitored.
如果我能偷…
Now, if I can sneak ...
威爾！我已經好了！
Will!  I'm not sick, anymore!
這沒什麼，爸爸
It was nothing, Dad.
凱撒，凱撒呢？我要見他
Ceasar.  Where's Caesar?  I want to see him.
凱撒！
Caesar!
他不可能走遠
He can't have gone far.
凱撒！
Caesar!
爸爸！
Daddy!
凱撒！
Caesar!
滾出去！滾！
Get out of here! Get out!
滾出去！
Get out!
喂，喂…夠了！
Hey, hey, hey ...  Enough! Enough!
你給我小心點
It doesn't matter what you do.
如果再讓我在附近看到這隻猴子…
If I catch that animal anywhere  near my house or my kids, again ...
他不會傷人
He's not dangerous.
不會有下次了
It won't happen again.
下次就不是這樣了！
Damn right, it won't!
- 走吧，爸爸   - 他只是想玩玩
Come on, Dad.  - He, he just wanted to play.
呆在家堙I有爸爸在
Stay in the house!  Daddy's got you.
說過不要自己出去了
I told you not to go out without us.
沒事了…
It's okay ...
怎樣？
How bad is it?
不清楚
I do not know.
他喜歡你
He likes you.  - Uh, huh.
別擔心，很快就會好
Don't worry. It'll be over soon.
那我們可以去吃好吃的了
Then, we can go get a treat.
我想吃冰淇淋
I'm thinking, ice cream.
好主意！
Good idea!
這手語你教他的？
You taught him to sign?
一點點基本動作而已
Just, handful of things, basic stuff.
他又在說什麼？
What's he saying?
沒啥
Nothing.
那我們什麼時候再來？
So, when do you think we should come back?
應該不用再來了
Well, you won't need to come back.
縫合線是可溶解的
because, um,  the stiches are dissolveable.
其他呢，注意觀察有無感染
I would just say, watch for  signs of infection.
發燒…猩紅什麼的
Fever ... redness ...
這次在說什麼？
Okay, what's he saying, now?
Um,
這…
well, ...
他覺得我們倆應該一起吃晚飯
he thinks that you and I should  have dinner together.
我…知道
(chuckling) I ... know ...
行了，凱撒！
Caesar! Come on!
很高興認識你，卡羅琳
Good to see you, again, Caroline.
別當燈泡了，凱撒
You coming, Caesar?
這是你的秘密嗎？
So, what's your secret?
噢，沒我什麼事，他生來如此
Oh, I can't take any credit.  It's in his genes.
你還挺厚道的
I think you're being very modest.
他真的很神奇
He's pretty amazing.
凱撒的小屋子很不錯嘛
I think you've built a pretty good  home for Caesar, here.
你知道他很快會長大的
You know he won't stay this way for long.
長成一隻威武勇猛的大猩猩
He's going to soon grow into
a large, powerful, animal.
過來！
Come here!
他怎樣最近？
How's he been doing?
還行
Okay, I think.
我喜歡黑猩猩
I love chimpanzees.
但也怕他們
I'm also afraid of them.
當然，怕是正常的
And, it's appropriate to  be afraid of them.
凱撒永遠不會傷人的
Caesar will never hurt anyone.
他在這堳雱祤畣\r}
He's happy here.
嗯，看出來了
Yeah, I see that.
但至少應該給他個開放點的空間吧？
We can at least give him some open space?
嗯，這是個好主意
- Yeah. That would prpbably be a good idea.
我知道金門大橋那邊有個地方
I know a place right across the bridge,
紅杉樹森林公園，簡直就是天堂
the Redwoods.  It's a paradise.
走吧！
Come on!
過來
Come here.
不用牽著他啦，沒事，走吧！
Doesn't need a leash!  He'll be fine. Come on!
- 安全一點   - 走吧，凱撒！
Just to be safe.  - Come on, Caesar!
這就是紅杉樹
It's the redwoods.
凱撒！
Caesar!
好吧
All right.
你可不要走遠噢
If I take this off you can  not leave my sight.
要不找不到你了
I'll never find you again.
好吧
Okay.
- 這是什麼意思？   - 他在幹嗎？
What's this?  - What's he doing?
- 太不可思議了！   - 什麼？
I don't believe that!  - What?
他在向你請示
He's asking your permission.
這是臣服的意思
It's a supplicating gesture.
好吧
It's okay.
走吧，凱撒！去吧！
Come on, Caesar!  Off you go!
快跟上！
Look at him go!
凱撒！
Caesar!
- 凱撒！   - 凱撒！
Caesar!!  - Caesar!!
凱撒！
Caesar!
你在這堙K
There you are ...
凱撒！
Caesar!
上去吧，凱撒，爬上去！
Come on, Caesar, climb!
往上！
Go higher!
爬啊！
Climb!
小心點！
Be careful!
小心，凱撒！
Caesar, be careful!
（五年後）
FIVE YEARS LATER
Hi!
怎麼了，夥計？
What's going on, buddy?
疼疼你
Give some love.
走，親愛的
Come on, honey.
那是黑猩猩嗎？
Is that a chimpanzee?
[dog snarls & barks]
走吧！
Come on!
[Caesar snarls back at dog]
[dog whimpers]
凱撒！…凱撒！
Caesar! ... Caesar!
快走！
Come on!
沒事啦，走吧
It's all right. Come on.
快進去
Come on!
我們走啦
Let's go.
你不進去嗎？
Are you getting in?
凱撒…
Caesar ...
怎麼了，夥計？
You okay, pal?
你是寵物嗎？…不是
Are you pet? ... No.
你不是寵物
You're not a pet.
我是你父親
I am your father.
那凱撒怎麼來的？
What is Caesar?
嗯…
Okay ...
凱撒，這是我工作的地方
Caesar, this is where I work.
也是你出生的地方
This is were you were born.
你媽媽和其他黑猩猩住在這喎\r}
Your mother was here  with other chimpanzees.
但她現在已經不在了…
But she's not here, anymore ...
所以…
so ...
我把你帶回家跟我一起住
... that's why I took home  to live with me.
嗯
Yeah.
你媽媽去世了
Your mother's dead.
她被注射了藥品
The thing is, she was given medicine,
也就是我給我父親用的藥
like the medicine I give to Charles.
她遺傳給你了
She passed it on to you.
所以你這麼聰明
That's why you're so smart.
帶他回家吧
Let's take him home.
來，跟我說說
Come on, explain it to me.
好吧
All right.
我把他從實驗室偷帶出來，救了他一命
I snuck him out of the lab  to save his life.
我那時不知道藥力遺傳給了他
I had no idea that the effects had  been transfered vertically from his mother.
但他從小就表現出超乎一般的智商
But, since then, he's been displaying  incredible signs intelligence.
我們研發112是為了療傷   但凱撒證明了藥用遠大於此
I designed the 112 to repair,  but Caesar's gone way beyond that.
這是他去年以來測量的智商
Here's his IQ from last year.
現在已經翻番了
Since then, it's doubled.
這樣不行
This is all wrong.
我父親差點就離開了人世，這支藥救了他
My father was on gone  this drug brought him back.
你不知道以前他什麼樣的
You never saw how bad he was.
他重獲新生了
He has his life again.
- 那凱撒怎麼辦？   - 什麼怎麼辦？
And, what about Caesar?  - What about him?
他怎麼過？
How does he fit in?
跟我過…跟我倆過
With me, ... with us ...
聽著
Listen, ...
我知道你很難接受事實
I know it has been hard for you,
但有些事情不能順著你的想法發展
but you are trying to control things  that were never meant to be controlled.
112藥劑是有用的
The 112 works.
你腦子清醒點好嗎？
Do you realize how you sound?
我只是說，這是件好事
All I'm saying is  this is a good thing.
凱撒證明了這一點
Caesar's proof of that.
我父親也一樣
So's my father.
凱撒，吃你的
Caesar, eat your food.
你沒事吧，爸爸？
Dad, are you okay?
嗯，我很好
Yeah, I'm fine.
抗體
Antibodies.
他的機體已經會抵抗112型藥劑了
His system has found a way  to fight the 112 virus
療效已經消失
so that it can't deliver  its therapy.
我父親的病要變本加厲地復發了
My father's disease is going  to return with a vengence.
住手！
Stop!
快住手！
Stop, right now!
喂！快出來！快下車！
Hey! Get out there!  Get out of that car!
你他媽在幹嗎？滾出我的車來！
What the hell are you doing?  Get out of my car!
聽見沒有，出來！
I said, get out of my car!
我是飛行員！我還要趕去機場！
I'm a pilot! I've got to get  to the airport!
現在我怎麼辦，嗯？
How am I gonna get there now, huh?
你他媽回答我！你在搞哪樣？
Answer the God-damn question!  What were you doing?
我的車跟這輛一樣…
I have a car just exactly ...
我無語了，讓警察來處理吧
I'm done ...  the police can handle it.
站住！你別想走，先生！
Stay right there!  You aren't going nowhere, mister!
你要賠我！
You will pay!
這都是你一個人的責任！
This is your problem,  you make it happen!
我跟你沒完！別走！
... not through with you!  Stay right there!
凱撒，住手！
Caesar, stop!
爸爸！
Daddy!
凱撒！
Caesar!
沒事了
It's okay.
他不是故意的
He didn't mean it.
沒事了…
It's okay ...
（動物管制）
喂，放開他！
Hey, hey, take that thing off of him!
放開他！
Take that thing off of him!
我帶他進去，行嗎？
Look, I'll take him in, okay?
不行，有法院執行令在，我們不能放開他
No, he's under court orders.  We can't do that.
沒事了！讓他帶進來吧
It's fine! Let him.
你們準備一下就可以進來
Bring him in when you're ready.
放開他
Take it off.
謝謝！
Thank you!
凱撒…凱撒
Caesar, Caesar, Caesar,  ... Caesar, Caesar.
現在不行，沒事的
Not right now.  It's going to be okay.
先看看堶惜偵羆邟a
Let's just see what it's like  inside, okay.
走，凱撒
Come on, Caesar.
我們進去
Let's go.
走吧，相信我
Come on, ... trust me.
沒事的
It's okay.
走
Go.
他沒有跟別的猩猩在一起呆過
He hasn't spent any time with other chimps.
噢，很正常
Oh, we're used to that.
一開始可能有點不習慣，不過我們會讓他合群的
He'll be a little skittish at first,  but we'll integrate him.
他們適應的速度會讓你吃驚的
You'd be surprised  how quick they adapt.
我們提供的是仿真的環境
We provide a stimulating environment.
他會過得很開心的
He's going to thrive here.
來吧，簽一下文件
Come, let's do some paperwork.
進來的時候記得鎖門
Make sure you lock that door  when you come in.
凱撒！
Caesar!
你沒事的！
You'll be okay!
很快就會好起來的！
Everything's going to be okay!
別怕
Don't be scared.
現在你得呆在這喎\r}
You're going to stay here, now.
不，還不能回家
No ... Not going home right now.
沒事的
It's OK.
分手時越依戀
The longer you drag out the good-byes,
越難以分開
the harder it is.
我等會兒簽字可以嗎？
Can I sign that later?
過不了多久你就是單相思了
You'll probably miss him more than  he'll miss you.
給他幾周時間適應吧
You'd best give him a couple of weeks  to get used too the place.
威爾，我們得走了
Will, we have to go.
我們要回家了
We have to go home.
很快會回來看你的，好嗎？
Coming back soon, okay?
記得先打電話給我
Just call ahead, before you do.
喂，看過來！
Hey, over here!
我能帶你出去！
Hey, I can get you out!
過來，這堙I
Come on!  Over here!
嗨，下面
Hey, down here.
傻猴子…
Stupid monkey ...
你想怎樣？這堿O瘋猴院，瘋猴院！
So you? Come on, make it!
法院執行令還沒發出來，所以系統堶惇d不到
Court order hasn't been filed,  so it's not in the system.
發出來以後
Once it comes through,
再過九十天你就知道上訴日期了
it will take about 90 days before  you receive an appeal date.
- 九十天？   - 沒錯，先生，九十天
90 days?  - Yes, sir, 90 days.
會有郵件通知你的
You'll be notified by mail.
你給我聽著
Here's what's going to happen.
打開電腦，看清楚
You're going to go back to your computer,  you know, shift things around
給我一個上訴日期，本周之內的，明白？
and you're going to get me a date for  my appeal, this week, you got it?
我幫不到你
I can't help you.
好吧，看來這事麻煩了
All right, then we have a problem.
你不給我操作，我就不走
Because, I'm not moving until you do.
九十天，先生   還給你上訴機會，謝天謝地吧
90 days, sir. Be thankful  you're talking about court dates.
沒直接弄死它算你走運了
You're lucky they  didn't put that animal down.
我很快會接他回來，爸
I promised to get him back  soon, Dad.
爸爸？
Dad?
父親的免疫系統繼續排斥112病毒
My father's immune system  continues to reject the 112 virus,
這種基因療法已經失效
rendering the gene therapy obsolete.
他的健康情況在惡化，疾病迅速擴散
his health is deteriorating,  and the disease is progressing rapidly.
我需要一種更強的病毒株
I need a more aggressive virus strain,
一種快速療法
a faster delivery method,
否則照這種情況下去…
because at this rate ...
我不能同時失去他倆
I can't lose them both.
我不會同時失去他倆
I won't lose them both.
喂…有時間談談嗎？
Hi .... Can we talk?
趕緊的，我要開會
Make it fast.  I've got a meeting.
你執掌基因系統公司這十年
The ten years you have been  running GEN-SYS,
出產過幾種可以拯救千萬條生命的藥？
how many drugs have come down the pipeline  that could save millions of lives?
革命性的藥？
That could change everything?
你什麼意思？
What are you talking about?
ALZ-112就是那種藥
The ALZ-112.
你怎麼了，威爾？
What happened to you, Will?
你曾經是實驗室的明星
You used to be the star of this lab.  Now, you hardly ever show
但看看現在的你，還有你的團隊
and when you do, you waste your time  and that of your team's
一直把時間浪費在這永遠拿不到許可的藥上面
fixating on a drug
that, after what happened,  is never ever going to get approved.
112是危險的，威爾
The 112 is dangerous, Will,
而且沒用
and it doesn't work.
我讓我爸試過了
I treated my father with it.
有用
It does work.
你，你說什麼？
You did, what?
你說什麼！？
You did, what!?
跟預想的一樣，制服了病魔
Beat the disease, like we predicted.
太好了
Brilliant.
但有並發癥
There's been a complication.
到底有用沒用？
Well, does it work or doesn't it?
我父親的疾病還是擊敗了病毒
My father's disease eventually  outran the cure.
老天吶
Oh, for goodness sake.
免疫系統產生的抗體擊敗了病毒
The immune system produced antibodies  to beat the viral component,
但它還是有用的
but it will work.
我已經研究出了一種病毒株
I've have already developed a virus strain
更激進的
that I think will be more aggressive.
你怎麼知道？
You think?
讓我試驗
Just, let me test it.
你在浪費我的時間
You're wasting my time.
我還沒說完！
There's more!
實際上，病毒不止能治病
The applications go beyond the disease.
我可以證明這種療法有助於增強認知能力
There are indications that show the  therapy can improve cognitive functioning,
還有記憶能力…
memory quality ...
等等，你什麼意思？
What, what are you saying?
我父親當時並不只是康復了
My father didn't just recover.
他變得更好了
He improved.
你意思是智商增長了？
You mean, increased intelligence?
並不能完全確定，不過我認為是的
It's not conclusive, but yes.
你馬上開始用猩猩試驗改進的112病毒   越快越好
I want you, to start testing the  revised 112 on chimps, A-S-A-P.
好
Okay.
要什麼儘管開口，馬上開始
I'll give you whatever you need,  but get started.
吃晚飯了！
Dinner time!
類人猿，你是靈長動物啊！
Great Ape, primate!
不認得飯嗎？
Go on, don't you know food  when you see it?
覺得好玩是吧？
You think that's funny, huh?
我讓你看看什麼才好玩！
I show you something funny!
很快你就知道這婼硐﹞F算
You'll learn who's boss, soon enough.
他的衣服怎麼辦？
What about his clothes?
什麼怎麼辦？
What about 'em?
不知道…但其他猩猩可能會有反應
I don't know ... May cause problems  with the other apes.
那最好！
Good!
一共十隻，沒錯吧？
I counted ten apes, correct?
嗯
Yep.
好，放到最後
Good.  All the way to the back.
進展這麼快，為什麼這麼急？
You guys are moving really quick on this.  What's the big rush?
第一天回來就看到你抱怨
First day back,  you're still complaining.
科巴，你好，我叫威爾
Koba. Hi, I'm Will.
就這只
This one.
他很淡定啊
He's very calm.
嗯
Yeah.
實驗室的常客了，相當配合
He's been through a whole lot of labs.  He knows the drill.
我能加入嗎？進度如何
Could I join you,  what's our progress.
幫他準備一下
Get him prepped.
戴緊面罩
Tighten your masks.
把113藥劑給我
Pass me the 113.
脈搏和氧含量都正常，血壓穩定
Pulse-ox is good,  blood pressure is steady.
準備好了
Perisol delivery, in place.
釋放113藥劑
Releasing the 113.
洩漏了！
We have a break!
富蘭克林，戴好面罩！
Franklin, get your mask on!
好了？
Got it?
嗯
Yeah.
沒事吧？
You okay?
嗯，沒事
Yeah, okay.
快出去！
Move it!  Let's go!
上去運動下，你們這些懶狒狒！
Get up and do some exercises  you lazy baboons!
智商測試令人驚嘆
Intelligence results are remarkable.
也沒有不良反應
There are no adverse effects.
類人猿的免疫系統很強
Apes have amazingly strong  immune systems.
很好，注意觀察
All right, keep an eye on him.
好
Okay. [Franklin sneezes]
不好意思
Sorry about that.
這些傢伙比我厲害多了
These guys are more resiliant than I am.
我出去一下
Excuse me a second.
（傷很重？）
You seriously injured?
（你也會手語？）
Do you know sign language?
（我在馬戲團呆過）
I worked at the circus.
這只可以
He's good.
（小心，人類不喜歡聰明的猿猴）
Be Careful. Humans do not like  intelligent apes.
你今晚加班呢
You're working late tonight.
基因系統公司還要三隻
GEN-SYS needs three more.
喂，凱撒！
Hey, Caesar!
你受傷了？
Are you hurt?
讓我看看
Show me.
凱撒，手給我看看，伸過來
Caesar, give me your hand.  Give me your hand.
新來的傢伙受欺負正常
Sometimes, the new kid on the  block gets picked on.
冷靜點，他們把你怎麼了！
Stay calm. What did they do?
狗屁！
That's bullshit!
怎麼回事？
What's the problem here?
我要帶他走，現在
I'm taking him out of here, right now.
沒有法院執行令，別想
Not without a court order, you're not.
他不再是你們的了
He's not yours, anymore.
相信我，如果被我發現他受虐
I promise, if I find out he's been  mistreated in any way,
我會讓你們這地方關門
I'll have this place shut down.
來啊
Go on ...
不，還不能回家現在
No.  No, we're not going home,  right now.
我會帶你出去的，我保證
I'm going to get you out of here,  I promise.
你要相信我
You have to trust me.
凱撒，你一定要相信我，好嗎？
Caesar, you have to trust me, okay?
時間到了
I think this visit's over.
相信我
Trust me.
你不會有事的
You'll be okay.
快上去！走吧！
Come on, move it!  Let's go!
有好幾百隻吧！   真像你的私人動物園！
There are hundreds of them!  Looks like you're own private zoo!
更像一個長毛動物監獄吧
Rather like a prison  for hairy dudes.
他們會看電視？
They watch TV?
充實一下生活
We call it enrichment.
哇，這只好可愛！
Aw, this one's so cute!
他叫什麼？
What's his name?
科尼利婭，是小mm
Uh, name's Cornelia. It's a she.
[shreek]
天吶！
Oh, my God!
別靠太近！
Don't get too close!
這只差點嚇死我
This one scared me half to death.
大個子叫莫奡程\r}
That big guy is called, Maurice.
這只不好玩
It's no fun.
來，我讓你看看好玩的
Here, I'll show you something fun.
你看！
Check this out!
你瘋了！
It's crazy!
你們怎麼能進來
You shouldn't be in here.
喂，小心我電你！
Hey, you're next!
我們走吧
Come on, let's go.
呆的時間夠久了
We spent too much time in here,  as it is.
走吧！
Come on!
看這傢伙
Check out this guy.
喂，亞倫，這小子不好惹   他自以為與眾不同
Hey, Alan, he's a pain in the ass.  He thinks he's special, or something
這眼神！
Freaky!
喂，過來
Hey, come here.
他好像在思考
I think he's thinking or something.
天吶，他掐住他脖子了！
Oh, my God, he's got him by the throat!
放開他！
Let him go!
我們走！
Let go!
你沒事吧？
Are you okay?
嗯
Yes.
跟你說別靠太近了，哥們
I told you not  to get too close, man.
我們出去吧
Come on, guys, let's get out of here.
有些事是改變不了的
Some things aren't meant  be changed.
要學會接受現實
You need to accept that.
喂！
Hey!
這是在幹嗎？
What's going on here?
更多的113藥劑實驗，我們在準備…
More 113 trials.  We're just prepping ...
不行，我們要先分析一下科巴的血樣！
Oh, no, we have to analyze  Koba's blood work first!
富蘭克林懂得的，他在哪堙H
Franklin knows this.  Where is he?
他請病假兩天了
He's out sick for two days.
我可沒讓你們這麼做
Well, I didn't authorized this.
是沒有！
No!
這是我的命令
I did.
我們說好只拿一隻好好試驗的
We agreed to test sparingly  on one subject.
但那只太令人興奮了！
And, that one subject is stunning!
這只是病毒，不知道人體效果
It's a virus. We don't know the human  related effects.
這東西有用，威爾
The drug works, Will.
跟他說說，琳達
Tell him, Linda.
作為一個初學者，科巴15步完成了漢諾塔
For starters, Koba scored  a perfect 15 on the Lucas Tower.
每次的實驗數據都證明有效
Every test result verifies  its effectiveness.
- 不要再試驗了   - 你這是…
No more tests.  - What are you ...?
先分析清楚
Not until we have a better understanding  of what we're dealing with.
我告訴你我們該怎麼做
Look, I'll tell you exactly  what we do. Look ...
我們倆說幾句話
Give us a minute.
請把猩猩關回籠子堙A輕點
Excuse me!   Put the ape  back in the cage. Be gentle.
威爾，情況我很清楚
Will, I'll tell you exactly what  we're dealing with, here.
我們在試驗的這種藥
We're dealing with a drug  that is worth more
比其他所有研究加起來還有價值
than everything else  we are developing, combined.
你青史留名
You make history,
我發我的財
I make money.
- 不是說好了嗎？   - 不行！有風險
Isn't that our arrangement?  - No! There are risks.
別扯什麼風險
Don't you tell me about risks.
你給你自己的父親用了實驗藥品
You give your own father  an experimental drug.
我一通電話就能結束你的職業生涯
I could finish your career  with one phone call.
省省吧，我不幹了
I'll save you the trouble. I quit.
沒你地球一樣轉
We will proceed without you.
聽著，你知道自己在做什麼嗎
Look ... You do not know what you're doing.
這些實驗必須要有控制
These tests need to be contained.
即使病毒株穩定了
You have no idea if the 113 is stable,
你也不知道他會對人類造成什麼傷害
what kind of damage it can  do to people ...
是啊，所以我們先拿黑猩猩做實驗，對吧？
Well, that is why we test it  on chimps, ... isn't it?
羅德曼博士，是我，富蘭克林！   請見見我！
Dr. Rodman, it's, me, Franklin!  I need to talk to you!
能開門嗎？
Can you come to the door?
博士！
Doc!  [coughing]
你他媽是誰？
Who the hell are you?  [Franklin sneezes on neighbor]
給我滾！
Get out of here!
對不起…不好意思
I'm sorry, ... I'm sorry.
你這不是要害我吧？
You wouldn't be trying to entrap me,  would you?
這個…不能說我同意了
Well, ... I can't say that I approve.
它們不是人，你知道的
They're not people, you know.
你到底放不放了他？
You gonna to let him go or not?
凱撒…嗨，走吧
Caesar, ... hey, come on.
走吧，我們回家
Come on, we're go home.
家
Home.
來，真的要走了
Come on, we're really going.
我們離開這喎\r}
Let's get out of here.
嗯…過來
Yeah ... Come on.
凱撒？
Caesar?
看來他還是喜歡同類多點
I guess he likes it better here  with his own kind.
（為什麼給餅乾，火箭？）
Why cookies, Rocket?
（一隻猴子…不堪一擊）
A single monkey ... is weak.
（一群猴子…團結就是力量）
Monkeys together - a force
（猴子就是傻）
Monkeys are stupid.
我擦，羅德尼
Damn it, Rodney,
你把水槍扔在院子堣F？
You leave the hose out in  the atrium, again?
什麼？不是吧
What?   No!
快點！上去吧
Come on!  Let's go.
快上去！
Come on, Get up!
電視：發射八個月後
[On TV] Eight months after its launch,
電視：第一支載人航空器飛向了火星
Earth's first manned space flight  to Mars ...
我沒撒謊，我說的是實話
I ain't dodging.  I'm telling the truth.
嗯，那要是你沒拿我的餅乾
Yeah, well, if I've didn't  take the cookies,
誰拿了？
Then, who the hell did?
我不知道…
I, I do not know ...
你們兩個白癡能消停會兒嗎？
Hey!  Will you two morons  knock it off!
我要回家了
I'm going home.
電視：表面有水源，所以可以支撐生命
[On TV] ... covered in water and  therefore able to sustain life.
就不能安靜一會兒
I get more peace in the  God-damned ape house.
對不起，爸！
Dad, I'm sorry!
富蘭克林先生，我是多蒂！
Mr. Franklin, it's Dottie!
富蘭克林先生？有人嗎？
Mr. Franklin? ... Hello?
什麼飛機？
What the hell?
羅德尼，快來平台
[Over radio] Rodney, get to the  platform, now.
羅德尼！
[Over radio] Rodney!
你他媽這是在演哪出？
What the hell do you think  you're doing, huh?
滾！
Get!
來啊！
Go on!
回你籠子堨h！
Get back in your cage!
我警告你！
I'm warning you!
回去！
Go on, get!
我受夠了！
That's it!
這就是後果！回去！
That's what you get! ... Get back!
你皮癢了嗎？
What's wrong with you?
傻猴子！
Dumb monkey!
你這只髒猴子，把臭爪鬆開！
Take your stinking paw off me,  you damn dirty ape!
不！
No!
我讓你們囂張！
I'll beat all!
卡羅琳，你去過凱撒的房間？
Caroline, have you been up to  Caesar's room?
沒人接
No one's answering.
蘭登！
Landon!
威爾！
Will!
怎麼了？
What happened?
他開口說話了
He spoke.
你…什麼？
What are you ... what?
你的猩猩…他說人話了
Your ape ... he spoke.
什麼鳥？
What in the hell?
我不相信
I don't believe this.
我讓你們囂張！
[Video] I'll beat each and  everyone of you.
需要洛城警署出動了
I need someone to coordinate  with the S.F.P.D.
告訴他們發生災難了
Tell them we got a fatality.
怎麼了？
What is it?
我知道他去哪堣F
I know where he's headed.
格倫？
Glenn?
快去！
Let's go!
雅各布斯
Jacobs.
雅各布斯先生，我是威爾組堛熊Y達
[Cell phone] Mr. Jacobs, It's Linda  from Will's team.
發生了很恐怖的事情
Look, something terrible  has happened.
富蘭克林病毒感染身亡了
Franklin is dead  from a viral infection.
你說什麼？
What the hell are you  talking about?
他被113藥劑感染了
He was exposed to the 113.  It does something
病毒對人有副作用
to people that it doesn't  do to apes.
我們得到橋那邊去
We'll have to go through the city  and across the bridge.
雅各布斯先生？你還在嗎…
[Cell phone] Mr. Jacobs?  Mr. Jacobs, are you ...
神馬意思？
What the hell?
我是史蒂芬·雅各布斯！
I am Steven Jacobs!
這堥麭B都是猩猩，我得上直升機！
It's full of apes in there.  I gotta get in the air!
我們得消滅他們
We have to be able  to destroy them.
請相信我，好嗎？
Just, trust me on this!  Okay?
趕緊把相機拿出來
You might want to get your cameras  ready.  Normally,
他們一般很害羞的
these guys are quit shy.
他們穿過公園了，在北邊！
They're going  the park,  on the north side!
找到帶頭的！
Find the lead!
說話要按按鈕！按鈕！
You gotta hold the button!  The button!
他們有帶頭的   這幫猴子比你們想像的聰明多了
They're being led.  These apes  are smarter than you think.
一定要幹掉帶頭的！
They've got a leader!
別說我堵在路上了，找個好點的理由！
Do not tell them I am stuck in traffic.  Make up with something smarter!
等等
Hold on.
這他媽…
What the ...
他們在橋上
They're on the bridge.
他們想要去紅杉林公園
They're trying to get to the redwoods.
洛城警署，第一小組
SFPD, Police 1.
這堿O空中部隊
This is Air Ops,
封鎖南邊橋頭，騎警什麼情況？
[On radio] Seal of south end.  What's the status of those units?
準備好了，長官
[Radio response] Ready to go, sir.
一旦靠近，就趕他們
[On radio] As soon as they reach you,  block them.
北邊的單位請注意   我們要把猴群趕向你們
[On Radio] North side, we're going to push  them right to you.
沒問題，我們準備好了
[Radio response] No problem.  We're ready for them.
北橋頭也封鎖了，它們別想跑走了
The north side is blocked.  [On radio] They'll never get through here.
一旦它們攻到缺口，我們就幹掉它們
As soon as they hit the gap,  we'll take them out!
- 你有把握？   - 甕中捉鱉
You can just shoot them?  Like shooting fish in a barrel.
很好！
Good!
馬上掉頭！
Turn that thing around!
請離開大橋，先生
Get off the bridge, sir.  I can't ...
- 你不明白   - 是你不明白，馬上離開！
You don't understand.  Get off this bridge, now!
現在在疏散，快走！
This is an evacuation.  Get out!
疏散所有民眾
All the civilians, clear.
請確認
[On radio] Please confirm.
讓他們趕緊離開大橋！
Put these people off the bridge!
騎警部隊，準備好！
Stand by, city mounted units!
要大屠殺了
They're gonna slaughter them.
我要去救凱撒
I'm gonna to get Caesar.
威爾！
Will, hey!
你小心點！
You, be careful!
我要回我車上去！
I gotta get to my car!
快離開！
Get out of here!
放開我！我要去車上！
Let go me!  I have to get my car!
往北邊趕
Push 'em north!
讓開！
Get out of the way!
趕緊，否則就被大霧擋住了！
下手！
Do It!
它們哪堨h了？看不見了！
Where are they?  I don't see them!
北橋頭，能看到嗎？
[On radio] CHP North,  do you have a visual?
看不見，長官
No, sir, negative.
打開保險栓！
Safety's off!
停火！
Hold your fire!
撤退！
Back!
凱撒！
Caesar!
就是他！他就是帶頭的！
That's him!   That's the leader!
進入視野！幹掉他們！
[On radio] They're in sight!  Put 'em down!
救救我！
Help me!
拉住我的手！
Take my hand!
快點…
Come, come on ...
拉住我！
Come on!
怎麼是你…
Not you ...
不要！
No!
救命！
Save me!
凱撒！
Caesar!
凱撒？
Caesar?
凱撒…對不起
Caesar ... I'm sorry.
是我的錯
This is my fault.
不能再繼續了
This has to stop.
這樣不是辦法
This isn't the way.
你知道他們的能耐
You know what they're capable of.
請跟我回家吧
Please come home.
回家後我會保護你
If you come home, I'll protect you.
這就是愷撒的家
Caesar is home.
很好
Okay.
凱撒已經回家了
Caesar's home.
去吧
Go.
-=TLF字幕組=-   翻譯：pizzamx   校對：pizzamx
Subtitles by Scorpion
謝謝觀賞   -=TLF字幕組=-